Finding Aid for Garnet R. Garrison Papers, 1928-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Garnet R. Garrison Papers 1928-1990
Garrison, Garnet R., 1911-
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
91443 Aa 2; UAm
Radio and television broadcaster; professor of speech at the University of Michigan; director of television, later director of broadcasting at the university. Biographical material, subject files relating to his career in broadcasting, published writings, speeches, scripts, and audio-visual materials; files document development of television at the University of Michigan, including various administrative and program changes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Garnet R. Garrison in 1990 (donor no. 2810 ).
The collection is open to research.
Garnet R. Garrison was born in Warrick County, Indiana in 1911. He received his B.A. from Wayne State University in 1933, and his M.A. from the University of Michigan in 1936. He married Isabelle M. Schelbe, also a WSU graduate. They have one daughter.
Garrison's career in broadcasting began during his student days at WSU when he worked as an announcer at Detroit area radio stations WEXL (1931) and WMBC (1932-1933). While working on his M.A. at the University of Michigan (1933-36), Garrison also worked as free lance announcer-director and newscaster at WXYZ, Detroit, and the Michigan Radio Network (1933-1934). He later joined the staff at radio station WJIM, Lansing as program director, copy writer, and political commentator (1934-1936).
In 1936, Garrison returned to Wayne State University as a lecturer in the Department of Speech. He taught the first courses in broadcasting at this institution, and also served as director of radio. He founded the WSU Broadcasting Guild. Garrison pioneered in the development of a system of audience measurement utilizing diaries, a technique which he continued to research and which became widely used in both radio and television.
During his time on the WSU staff Garrison continued graduate work at the University of Michigan, working on a Ph.D. in education, until his move to the National Broadcasting Company in New York City. During his years at NBC (1942-1947), he covered news and political events, produced several documentaries, and produced and directed many drama programs. He also taught broadcasting courses as a lecturer for Columbia University.
Garrison joined the Speech Department of the University of Michigan as a lecturer in 1947, was appointed associate professor in 1948, and professor in 1950 at which time he also became director of the newly founded Television Center. Under Garrison's direction, the University pioneered in the production and direction of educational TV programs. For several years, the TVC worked in cooperation with station WWJ-TV in Detroit. UM faculty would participate in television programs which were prepared and rehearsed on campus, and then props, scripts, staff, and faculty were transported to Detroit for the live production at WWJ studios. In 1951 stations WJIM (Lansing) and WKZO (Kalamazoo) began simultaneous broadcast of the live WWJ programs via a microwave relay hookup.
Station WOOD (Grand Rapids) began its own cooperative effort with the TVC in 1952 with the multi-part series "Understanding Our World." These programs were developed and rehearsed at the UM campus and then broadcast live from WOOD studios.
In 1953 WPAG, the UHF station in Ann Arbor, requested programming. The TVC provided studio facilities, equipment, and technical assistance, and the UM Speech Department provided student staff as part of its television production courses. Approximately 340 programs were broadcast from 1953 to 1957 when WPAG went off the air.
"Understanding Our World" (originally created for station WOOD) was continued in production by the TVC. UM faculty, and later, local, national, and international personalities, were featured. The format of the programs included interviews, panel discussions, demonstrations, and documentaries, and covered a wide variety of subjects.
The Television Center was also active in co-development with many academic areas of the university in the uses of instruction via closed- circuit television with particular emphasis in the Medical and Law Schools. The TVC documented the life of the university on film: physical changes on campus as new buildings were erected; ceremonies and celebrations involving faculty, students, and distinguished guests; and everyday student life and activities. The TVC also produced a number of films for public relations and educational purposes.
Over the years, the TV Center has received many television and film awards. The first came in 1955 from Variety, which gave the TVC the only Show-Management Plaque ever awarded an educational institution. Many national awards were also received by the stations WUOM and WVGR, and many series were produced for the national listening audience through the National Educational Radio Network.
Garrison was named director of broadcasting in 1958. His responsibilities expanded to include UM radio as well as television. Prior to this appointment, the two areas had operated independently with separate directors.
In 1972, Garrison relinquished the administrative post of director of broadcasting to resume fulltime teaching. He continued teaching until his retirement in 1979. Garrison was named professor emeritus of speech communication and theatre in recognition of his long and distinguished career as teacher, administrator, and broadcaster at the University.
Garrison was co-author (with Giraud Chester, NYC) of the textbook Radio and Television, published in 1950. This work was extensively revised in 1956 and published under the new title, Television and Radio. A third edition was published in 1963, co-authored with Giraud Chester and Edgar Willis (UM Speech Department). The fifth and last edition was published in 1978. This textbook was widely used by colleges and universities around the U.S.
Garrison wrote a number of articles and papers on listener diary techniques, broadcast techniques, and ongoing work in TV at the UM. He appeared on the programs of many regional and national speech and broadcasting conventions and seminars. Garrison was listed in Who's Who in America for several years during the 50's and 60's.
Garrison served on the Executive Council of the Speech Association of America and as a member of the Professional Advancement Committee of the National Association of Educational Broadcasters. He was also a member of the Michigan Association of Speech, the Educational Theatre Association, and the American Association of University Professors (AAUP). He served as the chairman of the Communication Arts Committee of the Michigan State Council for the Arts, (1966-1967). He belongs to the honorary fraternities Delta Sigma Rho (Speech), Phi Delta Kappa (Education), Pi Kappa Delta (Speech), and Phi Kappa Phi (Scholarship).
Following his retirement from the university, Garrison collaborated with Professor Alfred Slote (one-time student, faculty colleague, producer-writer at the UM Television Center, and longtime friend) in writing two mysteries Santa Claus Killer and Maze. These were written under the pen name of A.H. Garnet (A.H. from collaborator Alfred H. Slote). Santa Claus Killer was published in 1981, and Maze in 1982. The U.S. publisher was Ticknor and Fields, and the London publisher was Victor Gollancz Ltd.
The GRG papers span the years 1928-1990 and are divided into five series: Biographical Materials; Early Career; University of Michigan; Writings, Speeches, and Scripts; and Audio-Visual Materials. The collection traces Garrison's long and distinguished career in broadcasting, as well as his many years of teaching. The collection with few exceptions has been maintained in its original chronological order.
Subjects:
Garrison, Garnet R., 1911-; Radio broadcasting--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Television broadcasting--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Television in education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Broadcasting Service.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Media Resources Center.; University of Michigan. Television Center.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Broadcasting.; Garrison, Garnet R., 1911-; National Broadcasting Company, inc.; University of Michigan. Television Center.; Wayne University. Broadcasting Guild.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical Material
  Materials relating to Garrison's personal career advancement, to the prominent personalities from his early career, and author permissions have been placed in the first series, Biographical Material.
  - Career Summaries (Box 1)
  - Education 1928-1933
    - Eastern High School, Detroit, Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Wayne State University, Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Personal Miscellanea
    - Garnet R. Garrison (Box 1)
    - Prominent Colleagues and Students Miscellaneous Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
    - Author Permissions (Box 1)
- Early career
  The series -- Early Career -- is divided into three files: Wayne State University; WJIM; and National Broadcasting Company.
  - Wayne State University (Faculty) 1936-1942
    The Wayne State University, Faculty, file covers Garrison's experience as lecturer in the Department of Speech at WSU, 1936-1942. Garrison taught the first courses in broadcasting at this institution, and also served as director of radio. He founded the WSU Broadcasting Guild whose members wrote and directed programs which were presented over Detroit radio stations. Garrison pioneered in the development of a system of audience measurement utilizing diaries, a technique which became widely used commercially in both radio and television. Other files in this subseries are "WSU Reunion, 1986," and "Short Story Time."
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
    - Radio Activities Summaries, Radio Guild Activities and Membership Lists (Box 1)
    - Broadcasting Diary Techniques Research (Box 1)
    - WSU Reunion: Radio/TV/Film, Theatre Alumni 50th Anniversary 1986 (Box 1)
    - "Short Story Time," WSU on WXYZ 1937-1942 (Box 1)
  - WJIM Radio Station, Lansing 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    The WJIM file is relatively short (1934-1936), but demonstrates the scope and variety of programming in which GRG was involved. Garrison produced several programs relating to the history of Lansing, and the history of various political bodies in the State of Michigan.
  - National Broadcasting Corporation, New York City 1942-1947
    The National Broadcasting Company, NYC file is largely composed of newspaper clippings and publicity releases in the period 1942-1947. Garrison joined the National Broadcasting Company as director of the Employee Program Training Group. He later became production manager in charge of Drama, NBC Eastern Division. He directed several hundred radio dramas and documentaries, including "Home is What You Make It," (a public service series which won favorable recognition in John Crosby's column in Variety); "Words at War," (serious drama); "Archie Andrews," (situation comedy); "Grantland Rice Sports Stories," (action plays); and "Milestones on the Road to Peace," (two special one- hour documentaries, "VE and VJ Day"). In 1946-1947, Garrison also taught broadcasting courses as a lecturer for Columbia University. The classes were held at the NBC studios.
    - Employee Training Program (Box 1)
    - Dramatic Programming (Box 1)
- University of Michigan 1947-1979
  The series University of Michigan, 1947-1979 includes material reflecting Garrison's work as a teacher and as head of the Television Center. Of special note are the "Reports" folders highlighting areas of particular interest and concern to GRG from the years 1966-1972. The reports document progress in both radio and television, and those areas which Garrison wished to adapt and develop further. Other files - "GRG Scholarship Fund," "Sabbatical Leave," and "Retirement" - round out GRG's long and distinguished career. Correspondence and memorabilia demonstrate the long-lasting influence and impact he had among his many friends and colleagues.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, newsclippings (Box 1)
  - Textbook Radio and Television (Television and Radio, Revised Edition) (Box 1)
  - FCC: Planning for UM Television Station (Box 1)
  - Television Programming 1948-1973 (Box 1)
  - Television Center 1950-1973 (Box 1)
  - Reports:
    - "UM Radio Highlights, 1959-1960" (Box 1)
    - "Television Development at the University of Michigan," 1966 (Box 1)
    - "Television Report in Response to Memo From President Fleming," November 21, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Reports and Correspondence 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Sabbatical Leave 1972 (Box 1)
  - Garnet R. Garrison Scholarship Fund 1972 (Box 1)
  - Retirement Party 1978 (Box 1)
- Writings, speeches, and scripts
  The series - Writings, speeches, and scripts -- documents Garrison's creative life. The subseries, Published Mysteries, is subdivided into two sections: correspondence, newspaper clippings, and publicity releases relating to Santa Claus Killer, and materials which relate to Maze. These books were written post-retirement, and in collaboration with Professor Alfred Slote. There are two audio cassettes and a 7 1/2" reel-to-reel tape of radio interviews with Garrison and Professor Slote in the Audio-Visual series. Other portion of this series include Speeches, Scripts, and Printed Materials. These were collected throughout Garrison's career. "Milestones on the Road to Peace" was a major two- part documentary written and directed by GRG while at NBC. The collection contains audio cassettes of this program. The "Inspector General" script was a TV adaptation by John Rich, UM alumnus. Among the Printed Materials are a copy of the textbook Radio and Television, materials from Garrison's early days at WSU, and a dissertation written by James Lynch, UM student.
  - Published Mysteries Santa Claus Killer, and Maze, 1980-1983
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Publicity Releases (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Newspaper Clippings and Program Brochures (Box 1)
    - Speech Drafts
      - Miscellaneous Speech Drafts (Box 1)
      - "Television in the Modern World," 1957 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Drafts, 1 packets (Box 1)
      (GRG's Notes on 4" x 6" Index Cards)
  - Scripts
    - "The Romance of Lansing," WJIM circa 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Winchell's Santa Claus" by Frank Telford and Garnet Garrison circa 1939 (Box 1)
    - "Fibber McGee and Molly" by Frank Telford and Garnet Garrison, (Script Submitted to NBC) 1940 (Box 1)
    - "The Next is Always a Waltz" by Lynne Thompson, Director's Notes by Garrison 1943 (Box 1)
    - "The Other Mrs. Reeves" by Florence Bakalyar, Director's Notes by Garrison 1943 (Box 1)
    - "VE Day: Milestones on The Road," Director's Notes by Garrison (Box 1)
      (Actual Script Used in Part I)
  - Printed Materials
    - Radio Script Thesaurus, Wayne State University; GRG, Compiler, 1937 (Box 2)
    - The Wayne University Broadcasting Guild Radio Writing Handbook, By Walter McGraw, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Radio and Television: An Introduction, By Chester Giraud and Garnet R. Garrison, 1950 (Box 2)
    - "The Inspector General," As Broadcast Script June 2, 1951 (Box 2)
      (WWJ-TV, adaptation by Samuel J. Rich, now professionally known as John Rich)
    - A Study of the Size and Composition of the Viewing Audience of an Educational Television Program in the Detroit Metropolitan Area by James E. Lynch, 1954 (Box 2)
      (bound dissertation)
- Audio-Visual
  The Audio-Visual series includes photographs, audio cassettes, magnetic tapes, and videotapes which highlight major programs and milestones throughout Garrison's career.
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous black and white proofs and prints 1938-1989, 5" x 7", 8" x 10" (Box 2)
    - Collection of Miscellaneous Photographs Gathered for Garrison Retirement Party, University Club, Michigan Union April 22, 1978, 8" x 10" "Blowups" (Box 2)
    - Oversize Photograph (Composite) of Television Centre (Folder 1)
      (located in UAm)
  - Audio Cassettes
    - "Milestones on The Road to Peace," Part I, "VE Day," Part II, "VJ Day" (Box 2)
    - WJR "Focus," A.H. Garnet Interview, (Santa Claus Killer), 1981 (Box 2)
    - "Prime Time #397," Garrison Interview, (Santa Claus Killer), 1981 (Box 2)
  - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
    - Garnet R. Garrison "News," November 22, 1933, 5" reel (Box 2)
    - "Short Story Time," WSU, 7 1/2" reel (Box 2)
    - Excerpts from WSU Radio Guild Programs, 7 1/2" reel (Box 2)
    - WSU Radio Guild Party; GRG Move to NBC December, 1942, 7 1/2" reels
      - Radio Guild Members 1936-1938 (Box 2)
      - Radio Guild Members 1939-1940 (Box 2)
      - Radio Guild Members 1941-1942 (Box 2)
      - "This Is Our Garrison" (Box 2)
    - NBC Series, Aesop's Fables, "Home Is What You Make It," Produced and Directed by Garrison; Ben Grauer, Narrator, 7 1/2" reel (Box 2)
    - "The Santa Claus Killer," WUOM Interview, A.H. Garnet August 12, 1981, 7 1/2" reel (Box 2)
  - Videocassettes (VHS)
    - "Genius" 1958, b&w VHS (Box 2)
      (TV Center staff upon occasion of GRG's appointment as director of broadcasting. Farcical tracing of GRG's personal history.)
    - "Big Picture" 1958, b&w VHS (Box 2)
      (Farcical answer to question, "Who is Garnet Garrison?")
    - TV Center History, b&w VHS) (Box 2)
      (Excellent film tracing the history of the Television Center from years 1950-1973)
    - GRG-Dedication, Part I 1978, color VHS (Box 2)
      (Honoring GRG with a "Roast" at his retirement. Introduction by Hazen Schumacher summarizes GRG's career and history of TVC, lst of 3 segments)
    - Garrison, "Personal Messages" 1978, color VHS (Box 2)
      (GRG "Roast" continues. Taped tributes from GRG colleagues, students, and peers, 2nd of 3 segments)
    - Garnet R. Garrison Retirement "Roast" 1978, color VHS (Box 2)
      ("He made things happen"; comment by Professor Alfred Slote; concluding segment)
    - Christmas Shows 1964, 1965 1972., color VHS (Box 2)
    - Christmas Shows 1960-1976, color VHS (Box 2)
      (These shows have a comedic theme; a takeoff of a popular TV show, or a personalized story about TVC staff. Contain good shots of staff members, and one (1964) has shots of staff children at Christmas party.)